萌月&諸神字幕組
目覚めては繰り返す
Day after day, I awake in a daze,
mezamete ha kurikaesu nemui asa ha
目覚めては繰り返す　眠い朝は
眠い朝は
襟のタイをきつく締め
And fasten my collar tightly.
eri no tai wo kitsuku shime
襟のタイをきつく締め
教室のドアくぐると
As I walk through the door to my classroom,
kyoushitsu no doa kuguru to hon no sukoshi
教室のドアくぐるとほんの少し
ほんの少し胸を張って歩き出せる
I have the slightest bit of pride.
mune wo hatte arukidaseru
胸を張って歩き出せる
Then a wind rushed through that normal, everyday life.
sonna nichijou ni fukinukeru kaze
そんな日常に吹き抜ける風
そんな日常に
吹き抜ける風
聞こえた気がした　感じた気がしたんだ
I have a feeling I can hear it,
kikoeta ki ga shita
聞こえた気がした
I have a feeling I can sense it,
kanjita ki ga shitanda
感じた気がしたんだ
震えだす 今この胸で
Beginning to tremble within my chest.
furuedasu ima kono mune de
震え出す今この胸で
I have a feeling it's on its way,
mou kuru ki ga shita
もう来る気がした
As the millions of stars began to disappear,
ikuoku no hoshi ga kiesatteku no wo
幾億の星が消え去ってくのを
I sent them on their way,
miokutta
見送った
見送った 手を振った
Waving my hand,
te wo futta
手を振った
良かったねと
Whispering, "Congratulations".
yokatta ne, to
よかったね、と
ねえ　先輩
Come on, Senpai!
Let me try a new lock move on you!
Anti-Tenshi Operation HQ
新技　かけさせてくださいよ
It's called the Hundred-Twenty Lock!
名付けて逆二十字固め
One, two. Here we go, let's dance.
ねね　先輩ってば　ね　いいでしょ
Come on, please, Senpai. Can I?
"Here we go, let's dance"?
Let me try the new lock on you!
ね　ね　新技　新技
They're so cute. Aren't they, Shiina-san?
可愛いですね　ね　椎名さん
浅はかなり
How unwise.
しかっとすか
マジっすか
もうイイ
Gosh. Is this grade school? We're just gaining kids one after another here.
ったく　ここは小学校かよ
大山先輩にかけよう
ガキばっか増えてくな～
キサマ　ボクに言ってるのか
You. Are you referring to me?
I'm God, remember.
ボクは神だぞ
Huh? You're still going on about that?
あっ　まだそんなこと言ってんのかよ
音無に抱きついて大泣きしてたくせによ
You were clinging onto Otonashi, crying your eyes out.
Who cried, you said?
誰が泣いたって
You're the one who will be crying...
泣くのはキサマだ
For example, recognise how useful a clothespin is.
さ　洗濯ばさみの有能さに気付くんだ
洗濯ばさみにも劣る自分の不甲斐なさを嘆くがイイ
Lament over how you're even less useful than a mere clothespin...
翻譯夏矢今瘋
臺本眯眯 奔奔
C-Clothespin...
洗　洗濯ばさみ
特效 saber 時間&後期 月染不透
校對　矢今瘋小夜子
It can clip.
はさめる
挟んで落ちない
By clipping, it keeps things from falling.
洗濯物が汚れない　素晴らしい
Meaning the laundry won't get dirty!
萌月諸神聯合譯製
It's amazing!
クリップ代わりに髪を挟んだりとか応用も利く使える！
It can even be used as a hair clip if need be!
Compared to that, what good am I?!
それに対して　オレはなんなんだ
なんの役割も立てない
I can't do anything! I'm not worth anything!
You. Don't use hypnosis just to let off steam.
お前　催眠術を腹いせに使うな
音無さん　おはようございます
Otonashi-san. Good morning.
What was this about?
あれは何だ
He bothered me first.
あっちからさきにつっかかってきたんです
I tried to wrap up the matter as amicably as possible.
ボクは　できるだけ穏便に
How is this amicable?
どこが穏便だ
大の男が跪いて大泣きしてるじゃないか
You made a grown man fall to his knees and cry.
Otonashi-kun. Naoi-kun.
音無君　直井君
用があるの　ちょっとこっちにきなさい
I've got something for you two. Come here.
Vacant Room
Teacher's Building 3rd Floor
What do you want, calling us out here?
何だよ　こんなところに呼び出して
Naoi-kun, I want you to restore Otonashi-kun's lost memories.
直井君　音無君の失われた記憶を戻して見せて
ボクに命令だと
You're ordering me?
さきから　キサマ何様のつもりだ
Who do you think you are?!
She's your leader. Your boss.
てめえのリーダーだ　上司だよ
Be obedient and listen to her.
おとなしく言うことを聞け
Wait, my memories?!
って　オレの記憶
Yes, your memories.
そうよ　あなたの記憶
Naoi-kun's hypnosis is the real thing.
直井君の催眠術は本物よ
あなたの失われた記憶も取り戻せるはず
You should be able to regain the memories you lost.
うん　なるほど
I see. I would like to take part in that.
それは僕の手でなんとかしてみたいですね
Hold on! Don't go deciding this without me.
ちょっと待てよ　かってにそんなこと決めんなよ
Why not?
どうして　まさか忘れたままでいたいの
Don't tell me you want to remain oblivious as to your past?
Well...
あっ　それは
Sure, I want to remember.
もちろん思い出したい
But, what is this anxiety?
けど　この不安は何だ
Could it be that I'm worried that this life will end if I remember?
それはもしかしたら　オレの記憶のせいで
この生活が終わってしまうんじゃないかと
オレは　オレはこんなにもみんなとの暮らしを気に入っていたんだ
I...
I didn't know I was enjoying this life with everyone this much.
But, when I remember my past,
でも　過去を思い出してしまってそれでもこれまでどおり
will I be able to spend time with them the same way I have been?
一緒に過ごしていけるのだろうか
でも　それでも
Even then-
音無君
Otonashi-kun?
H... Huh? Oh, yeah.
Sure.
わかった
No matter what past you see, please don't lose sight of yourself.
どんな過去を見ても
どうか自分を見失わないで
もしあなたがどうなっても　ボクだけは味方ですから
No matter what happens to you, I alone will be at your side.
なにか言ってください
Please say something.
I'll be at your side, too, so relax.
あたしも味方だから　安心しなさい
Yeah, that's reassuring.
あ　頼もしいよ
Huh?! What's the difference?
あ　なに　この差
Well, fine.
まぁイイです
どうぞ座ってください
Please have a seat.
Okay, let's begin.
では　はじめます
Is school fun, Onii-chan?
お兄ちゃん　学校楽しい
Not at all. I don't even go there.
楽しくはねえよ
行ってねえから
Otonashi Hatsune
It might be fun if you go.
行ったら楽しいかも知れないよ
Maybe, if I was smart.
アタマがよかったら楽しいかもな
オレバカだからな
I'm an idiot.
成績悪いやつには　居場所がないところだ
To people with poor grades, like myself, it's no place to be.
勉強は楽しくない
Isn't studying fun?
How could it be? It's studying.
楽しいわけないだろう　勉強だぞ
How about friends? Is playing with your friends fun?
友だちは　お友だちと遊ぶのは
I'd rather watch TV or play games alone.
一人でテレビ見たり　ゲームしてる方が楽しい
相手の趣味に強引に付き合わされたり
It's a bother to cater to what others want to
do and laugh at jokes that aren't even funny.
面白くもない冗談にわらってやらなきゃいけなかったり
疲れるだけだ
Really? I'm looking forward to studying.
そう　ワタシは勉強楽しみだな
I look forward to making friends, too.
友だちつくるのも楽しみ
あっ　そうだ
Oh, right.
Here.
これ
Thank you, Onii-chan.
ありがとう　お兄ちゃん
Ass hole!
馬鹿野郎！
I don't understand the point in life.
オレは生きている意味がわらかない
I don't get the meaning.
生き甲斐を知らない
他人に興味が持てない
I can't even seem to build interest in others.
I live without getting involved with others because that's just easier.
誰ともかかわらずに生きるのは　そのほうが楽だからだ
最低限食っていけるだけのアルバイトを惰性で続けて
I'm satisfied to work sluggishly part-time, making just enough to eat.
そんな暮らしで充分だった
Even then, I always go to see my sister.
それでも　オレはずっと妹にだけは会いに行っていた
With the little money I make, I buy her manga.
なけなしの金で
マンガ雑誌を買っていく
I randomly choose one from the stack, so I don't even know if I'm buying her duplicates.
いつも適当に本屋で平積みになっているのを買っていくから
同じ雑誌かどうかすらわからない
I might be buying a different title each time, too, so that the story never flows.
もしかしたら　違う雑誌になっていて
話は続いていないのかもしれない
でも
Still...
Thank you, Onii-chan.
ありがとう　お兄ちゃん
My sister always says that.
妹は決まってそう言った
結局　なんでもうれしいようだった
She seems to be happy with anything I give her.
妹はオレとは違う
She's different from me.
生きることに希望を持ってるし
She has hope in life, so I'm sure she'll find purpose, too.
生きる意味もきっと見つけられる
Yet, these past two years, she's been stuck in the hospital.
なのに　ずっとこの二年
退院できないまますごしている
かわいそうに
Poor thing. If only I could switch with her.
変わってやれたらイイのに
If she could switch with me, who has no hope nor purpose in life...
何の希望も持たない　生きる意味もわからないこのオレと
その憐情の想いがオレをここに通わせていた
These are the thoughts that make me come back here.
Winter's come.
冬になった
Summer is a tough season to work, but winter is even worse.
夏もそうだけど
冬のバイトはいっそう辛い
My fingertips are so cold, they feel like they'll chip off.
指先が悴んで　裂けそうだ
それでも
Even then, I'll continue to work so I can live.
生きるために続ける
生きる？
"Live"? What for?
なんのために
No, I can't think about that.
考えちゃダメだ
If I think, I might even quit working.
考えたらバイトすらやめてしまいそうだから
これだけはつづけなきゃな
I have to continue working like this,
so that I can live, and buy presents for my sister.
食うために
そして　妹にプレゼントを買ってやれるように
そうだ
Oh yeah. On Christmas,
クリスマスは医者に相談して
I'll ask the doctor to let her go outside, even if for just a little while.
少しだけでも外に出られるようにしてもらおう
車椅子は雪が積もると使えないのかな
Do wheelchairs become useless in snow?
If so, I'll carry her on my back.
だったらオンブでイイや
I'd walk to the ends of the Earth, if she were on my back.
あいつ一人ぐらい　いくらでもオブって歩ける
Then, I'll buy whatever she wants, wherever she wants.
それで好きな店で好きなものを買ってやろう
If possible, I want to let her have some cake at a nice store.
できれば
イイお店でケーキも食べさせてやりたい
Looks like I need to make more money.
っだと　もっと稼がないとかな
クリスマス出歩けるならどんな場所に出かけたい
If you could go out on Christmas, where would you want to go?
The main street in the city.
町の大通り
Somewhere like that?
あんなとこでイイのか
All the trees will be lit up. Did you know?
だってね～
全部の木に電気が付くんだよ
知ってる
いや　クリスマスにあんなとこ行かねーし
No. I never bother to go places like that at Christmas.
I heard it's really beautiful.
すごくキレイなんだって
They started doing it just last year. The doctor told me.
去年からそうなんだって
先生がね　言ってた
んじゃそこ行くか
Then, you want to go there?
行けるの
I can?
I'll ask if you can.
行けるように掛け合ってみる
もしダメでも
Even if they say no, I'll sneak you out.
内緒でつれてってやるよ
Really?
ほんと
Yeah, I mean it.
あ　ほんと
Yay! Thank you, Onii-chan!
やった
ありがとう　兄ちゃん
これまでで一番大きな「ありがとう」だった
That's the biggest "thank you" I've ever had from her.
What are you doing?
なん　なにやってんの
あっ　すみません
I'm sorry!
バイトの掛け持ちをはじめた
I've started working several other part-time jobs.
家では寝るだけになった
At home, all I do is sleep.
I feel able to work because I have motivation to.
今は目的があるから働けている気がする
The one thing I worry over is how her condition is only worsening.
ただ一つ心配なのは
あいつの容体が悪くなっていることだった
Permission to go out obviously wasn't granted.
外出の許可は当然出なかった
だから　オレは
So after visiting hours, I snuck into her room, and took her out to the night time city.
面会時間が終わったあと
病室に忍び込み　妹を夜の町に連れ出した
Wow! Hey, do you see these? They're amazing.
すげー
おい　見えてるか
すごいぞ
あ　すごくキレイ
Very pretty.
Yeah. They're really pretty.
だな～
すごくキレイだ
I'm glad I got to see them, too.
オレも見られてよかったよ
It's all thanks to you.
お前のおかげだな～
Well, the fun continues.
さ～て　これから楽しい時間が続くぞぉ
まずはプレゼントだ
First, we'll get your present.
なんでも買ってやる
I'll buy you anything you want.
兄ちゃん　この日のために実はすげー貯金貯めてきたんだぜ
I made lots of money just for today.
So I can buy you anything, no matter the price.
だから　どんな高いものでも買ってやれる
なにがほしい
What do you want?
まず店に入ろうか
How about we go check out some shops?
We can even go to a jewellery store.
宝石店でもイイぜ
普通にデパートがイイか
Or do you want to go to a department store?
兄ちゃん
Onii-chan...
うん
ありがとうね
Thank you.
あ
Sure.
買い物のあとにもな
There's a surprise waiting after we go shopping, too.
イイこと待ってるんだぞ
We'll go to dinner!
こんどは夕飯だ
I've not been there myself,
よくわからないけど
雑誌に載っていたイイ店　予約してあるんだ
but I put in reservations for a nice restaurant I found in a magazine.
There'll be a full-course meal.
コースで決まったものが出てくるんだぞ
A full-course meal, I tell you. Isn't that amazing?
コース料理だぞ
すごいだろ
そのあとも　オレはひとりでしゃべり続けて　歩き続けた
I continued to talk and walk.
Then if you'll excuse me, I'll be off.
では　行きます
Are you continuing to live alone in that house?
このまま一人であの家で暮らしていくの
It'll be lonely.
さびしいだけでしょ
大丈夫です
I'll be fine. I'm used to it.
慣れてますから
Are you sure? Will you really be all right?
そう
ほんとに大丈夫かしら
困ったことがあった　いつでも言っておいでね
If anything comes up, let me know.
You can come for dinner any time you'd like, too.
ご飯だっていつでも食べさせてあげるから
はい
Yes. Thank you very much.
ありがとうございます
このたびはほんとにお世話になりました
Thank you so much for your kindness.
I had a purpose in life.
オレはちゃんと生き甲斐を持って生きていたんだ
That purpose had been right beside me, all along.
生きる意味は
すぐそばにあったんだ
I just never noticed.
気づかなかっただけだ
オレはあいつに「ありがとう」そう言ってもらえるだけで
I was able to live on just hearing "thank you" from her.
生きていられたんだ
あいつに感謝されるだけで
Her gratitude was enough to make me feel alive.
生きた気がしたんだ
シアワセだったんだ
I was happy...
I was such an idiot.
バカだ　オレ
To only notice this now...
今ごろ気づくなんて
そんな大切な存在だったのに
She meant so much to me, yet I couldn't do anything for her.
なにもしてやれなかった
ずっと
All she ever did was read the manga I brought for her at the hospital.
あいつは病院で　オレの買ってきたマンガ雑誌読むだけで
それだけで
Was she... Was she really happy with her life, that consisted of just those things?
それだけの人生で
あいつはシアワセだったのだろうか
And, now that I've lost her, has my life ended, too?
そして
それを失ったオレの人生も終わってしまったのだろうか
My days had been filled with a happiness that I hadn't even realised existed.
気付かない幸せに満たされていた日々
Those days are gone.
その時間は過ぎ去ってしまった
もう　俺には　なにも残されていない
I don't have anything by my side any more.
お世話になりました
Thank you so much.
Congratulations.
退院おめでとう
ありがとうございました
Thank you very much!
元気でね
Take care of yourself.
I might be able to find purpose in life again.
俺はもう一度　生き甲斐を見つけられるかもしれない
I think I can find meaning in it again.
生きる意味を見つけられるかもしれない
If I could spend my life for someone else...
誰かのために　この命を費やせるのなら
Otonashi Yuzuru
College Application Ballot
思い出した
Have you recalled?
ああ
Yeah.
It doesn't sound like you had a pleasant life.
素晴らしい人生だったとは言えそうもないわね
しばらく　ひとりにしてくれ
Could you leave me alone for a while?
惰性で生きて　無気力だった俺は
I once lived sluggishly and without putting in any effort,
自分の生きる理由をお前に教えてもらって
but you taught me the purpose of life.
I found that purpose,
and I died in the middle of working toward the dream I'd found?
見つけて　それで
夢半ばで死んだのか
I died without accomplishing anything?
なにも成し遂げずに死んだのか
そんなのってねえよ
That's just not right... It's not right!
ねえよ
死に切れねえよ
I can't die off like that...
Hatsune!
初音
Have you calmed down?
落ち着いた
うん
Yeah.
People's hearts are unstable for a while after they regain their memories.
記憶が戻ってしばらくは　心は不安定なものよ
So you're not the only one.
あなただけじゃないわ
俺は弱いな
I'm weak, aren't I?
That just emphasises how strong you are.
お前の強さが改めてわかった
That's not true.
そんなことないわ
それで　何か変わった
So, did something change?
ん？
Your feelings. Are you going to keep working with the Battlefront?
気持ちよ
これからも「戦線」に居続けるの
I will.
居続けるよ　このままじゃ死に切れねえし
I can't go rest in peace yet.
I see. So now you have motivation, too.
そう　あなたにも目的が生まれたってわけね
Yeah, so I look forward to working with you again.
ああ　改めてよろしく
うん
モエのつきカミガミ
Headmaster's Room
で　報告ってなに
So, what report do you have for me?
本日の食券が不足しているとのことです
We're short on today's meal tickets.
どうする　「トルネード」いっとくか
So what? Wanna do Tornado?
No. Today's operation will be Monster Stream.
いや　今日のオペレーションは「モンスターストリーム」よ
Monster Stream
It's finally here!
ついにきおったか
絶望のカーニバル
carnival
It's a carnival of despair.
What is this operation?
なんなんだ　その作戦は
モンスターなんてのがいるのかよ　この世界には
Is there a monster living in this world?
Yes. It's the Lord of the River.
ええ　川の主です
"Lord of the River"?
川の主
There's a river not too far from here, right?
ちょっと歩いたところに川があるだろ
Monster Stream
そこで食料の調達だ
We'll be gathering food from there.
I-Isn't that just fishing?
そ　それってもしかして単なる川釣りなんじゃあ
そうだけど　それがどうかしたか
That's right. Is there a problem?
ああ　いや
Ah, no...
またつられて馬鹿な想像をしてしまった
They sent me off on another stupid fantasy...
今回は誰が勝つかね
I wonder who will win.
Botanical Garden
いや　楽しみだな
I can't wait.
そんなとこで何してんだ
What are you doing there?
Weeding and various other things.
草むしりとか　いろいろ
そ　そうか
I-I see. Oh, right!
あっ　そうだ
おまえも来いよ
You should come, too.
Hm?
今から皆で川釣りに行くんだ
We're all going fishing at the river.
かわ？
"River"?
あそこに近づくのは校則違反よ
It's against the school code to go near there since it's dangerous.
危ないから
What's the big deal?
いいじゃないかよ　お前だってもう生徒会長じゃないんだし
You're not the student council president any more.
Break the rules all you want.
破ってやれよ
でも　生徒だから
But I'm still a student.
お前　なんてやつ連れてくんだよ
Just who are you trying to bring?!
いいじゃないか　混ぜてやろうぜ
Come on. Let's have her come along.
敵だぞ　我らが戦線の宿敵だぞ
She's our enemy! She's the Battlefront's nemesis!
He's a dumbass!
阿呆ですね
How unwise.
あさはかなり
Listen to me. She's harmless now. She's not our enemy any more.
聞いてくれ　もう無害だ　敵じゃない
だが　曲りなりにも元生徒会長だぞ
But she's the former student council president!
ちなみに　現生徒会長代理もいますが
Incidentally, the deputy president is with us.
Exactly.
その通りです　が　その前に僕は神です
But more than that, I'm God.
I told you, you aren't!
神じゃないっつってんだろ
What are we going to do, Yurippe?
どうすんだよ　ゆりッペ
She's not the president any more, so why not?
もう　生徒会長でもないし　いいんじゃない
だっ　大丈夫かよ
Y-You sure about this?
なんかすごいメンバーになりつつあるな
Our member list is getting crazy...
Come to think of it, no one brought anything with them.
そういや　皆手ぶらじゃないか
すでに　ギルドへ連絡はいってるから大丈夫さ
A notice was sent to the Guild, so don't worry.
そういうマニアもあそこにはいる
They sent the maniac.
Riverbed
Below Second Bridge
"Maniac"?
マニア
Who's he?
彼は？
斉藤ってやつだ
That's Saitou.
He knows lots about guns, too,
銃にも詳しいが
but he's a fishing maniac so the Guild calls him Fish Saitou.
ギルドではフィッシュ斉藤と呼ばれる釣りマニアでね
このオペレーションの時だけは
When we do this operation, he comes to the surface with fishing equipment on a cart.
大量の釣り道具を荷車で引いて地上まであがってくる
He brings them from that far away?
あの距離をか
どんだけ釣り好きなんだよ
Just how much does he love fishing?
Basically, he's another dumbass.
要は阿呆ですね
よし　始めるか
Okay, let's start!
阿呆だ
What a dumbass...
If I hadn't asked that stupid question in the beginning, I might have been on your side.
この世界で俺は　お前の味方でいたかもな
There's no one like that.
そんな人はいなかったわ
Well, there can be one, right?
いてもいいじゃないか
There isn't one. Even if there were, they'd disappear.
いないわ
いたとしても　みんな消えちゃうもの
Tachibana.
タチバナ
俺達は消えない
We won't disappear.
So you can get along with us.
だから　仲よくしてもいいんだよ
Here. Let's fish with everyone.
ほら　皆と一緒に釣りしよう
Ow! Ow! Ow! You hooked it on me!
What do I do next?
ここからどうするの
違う　違う
Not quite like that.
まずはルアーか　餌を針の先につけるんだ
First, you use a lure or put some bait on the hook.
So, you're okay with worms, huh?
お前　虫平気なんだな
次は
What's next?
川に向かって竿を思い切り振って見ろ
Swing the rod toward the river as hard as you can!
T-Takeyama!
竹山
Call me Christ!
「クライスト」とーーーッ
Wow, you've got some amazing strength...
つかおまえ　すごい怪力だな
Overdrive is in passive mode.
オーバードライブはパッシブだから
パッシブ？
"Passive"?
もしかしたら
Maybe... Maybe, she might be able to do it.
もしかしたら　あんたならいけるかもしれないな
Do what?
なにがだ
主を釣り上げるってことよ
Catch the Lord of the River.
そいつはオペレーションネーム通りの化け物なのさ
It's a real monster, just like the operation name.
なにか引いてる
Something's tugging.
M-Monster Stream!
モ　「モンスターストリーム」
ああ　これが
You mean this?!
本来モンスターストリームは主の怒りの証
Originally, Monster Stream was a sign of the lord's anger.
これが起きたら　すぐ全員離脱
When this happens, everyone takes cover.
だが　その子なら　もしや
But if it's her, then maybe...
マジでやんのかよ
Are we really going to do this?
どんだけでかいんだよ　竿が折れるぞ
Just how big is it? The rod's going to snap!
おいらの腕を侮ってもらっちゃあ　困る
I don't want you to underestimate my skills.
It's made so it can fight against the lord!
主にも耐えられる特製だ
Even so, this isn't going to let us pull it up!
だとしても　このままじゃ　ぜってえ無理だ
What? Are you guys trying to catch the lord?
なんだよ　主をやる気か
正気じゃねえな
They're out of their minds.
Matsushita Fifth!
松下五段
肉どん優先して回してやるから　手伝え
I'll give you the beef udon ticket, so help out!
おいよ
Bring it on!
Oh, Hinata-senpai, you're so full of openings.
おっと　日向先輩　隙だらけじゃないんですか
よし　股の間思い切り蹴りあげてみよう
Maybe I'll take this chance to get a firm kick in.
Stop being cheap and help out, too!
姑息なこと考えてないで　お前も手伝え
もっとだ　加勢しろ
We need more help!
Otonashi-san!
音無さん
What the... What a weak bunch.
柔なやつだ
Pull! Pull! Pull! Pull! Pull! Pull!
おら　やろども　もっと照り合いいっぺ働け
Come on, gang! Pull it like you mean it!
エス　オー
Now!
今だ
She got it out of the water!
釣りあげやがった
Yeah, with us!
俺達ごとかよ
Who's the monster here?
どっちがモンスターだよ
Look out!
んにこの状況
This isn't good.
まずいですね
このまま落ちたら　食われるぞ
It'll eat us if we fall straight down!
Crazy for you!
God never falls.
神は落ちない
How unwise.
あさはかなり
It's going to eat us!
食われる
I must save them.
助けなきゃ
なあ　これあったら　しばらく「トルネード」しなくていいんじゃねえ
Hey, with this, I don't think we'll have to do Tornado for a good while.
え　毎日これ食べるの
What? We're going to eat this every day?
いや　それ以前にどうやって保存すんだよ
More like, how are we going to preserve this?
ん
捨てるのも何だしな
It'd be a waste to throw it away. Can't be helped, then.
仕方ない　一気に調理して一般生徒にもふるまうか
How about we cook it up and offer it to the NPCs?
Yeah, you're right.
ああ　そうだな　そうすっか
I guess that's the only way.
It's like we're volunteering, huh?
まるで　慈善事業だな
Forget the Battlefront. We're becoming some kind of charity organisation.
戦線どころか　なにかの奉仕団体になってるぞ
でも　戦う相手もいなくなっちゃったし　戦線でもなくなるのかな
But, we don't have an enemy to fight against, so will we really still be the Battlefront?
Then what else are we gonna be?
んじゃあ　一体何になるってんだよ
いつも一人で歩いてた
The "Slackers-So-We-Don't-Disappear Team"?
消えないように「ぐうたらしてますチーム」
What kinda name is that?
なんでぃそりゃ
振り返るとみんなは遠く
●
Chop, chop, chop, chop.
チョップ　チョップ　チョップ
●
まさか　こんな時間が来るとは思わなかった
I never thought a time like this would come.
●
それでも私は歩いたそれが強さだった
Hey, Tachibana.
なあ　タチバナ
Can I call you by your first name?
下の名前で呼んでいいか
Why?
どうして
●
親しくなったからだよ
Because we're closer now.
We are?
なった
You mean we aren't?
なったじゃないか
一緒に釣りして　一緒に料理して
We fished together and we're cooking together.
●
それに　最初から思ってたんだよ
Besides, I've thought ever since you told me...
もう何も怖くない
きれいな名前だなって
You have a pretty name.
I really like your name.
好きだよ
おまえの名前
そうつぶやいてみせる
奏って　音を奏でるって意味だろう
It's "Kanade" as in "to play music," right?
あなたがそうしたければ　どうぞお好きに
If that's what you wish, then please do.
My first name is Yuzuru.
俺の名前は結弦
弦を結ぶって書いて結弦
You write the "tie the strings" part in kanji. Call me that, too.
．
いつか　人は一人になって
そう呼んでくれていい
うん
So, Kanade... I have a favour to ask.
じゃあ　奏
聞いてほしい頼みがあるんだ
What is it?
なに
これからも　皆と一緒にいてくれ
Will you continue to hang out with us?
思い出の中に生きてくだけ
どうして
Why?
もう誰とも　戦ってほしくないから
Because I don't want you to
fight against others any more.
孤独さえ愛し笑ってられるように
I want you to have fun with everyone.
皆と楽しく過ごしてほしいから
その　それに
And, plus...
俺もお前と一緒にいたいからな
I want to be with you, too.
私は戦うんだ
そう
I see. If that's what you're telling me to do, then I will.
あなたがそういうなら　そうする
涙なんて見せないんだ
約束だからな
It's a promise, you hear?
うん
Okay.
そういや　ゆりっぺは
Where did Yurippe go?
おっ　言われてみれば　見てねえな
Oh yeah, I haven't seen her.
I bet she was watching us from somewhere high and above.
どうせどっかで高見の見物だろぉ
She wouldn't participate in a volunteer activity like this.
こんな奉仕活動みてえなことに参加する玉かよ
Hey! Why don't you help, too?!
つか　てめえも手伝え
ゆりっぺ
Yurippe!
Yurippe! Who did this to you?!
ゆりっぺ　誰にやられた
天使
Tenshi.
Tenshi?
天使？
Hold on! Kanade was with me this whole time!
待てよ　奏はずっと俺といたぞ
天使…
Tenshi?
I've always walked this path alone; when I look back, everyone is so far away.
itsumo hitori de aruiteta furikaeru to minna ha tooku
いつもひとりで歩いてた　振り返るとみんなは遠く
Even so, I kept on walking. That was my strength.
soredemo atashi ha aruita sore ga tsuyosa datta
それでもあたしは歩いた　それが強さだった
"Nothing frightens me any longer", I mumble softly.
mou nanimo kowakunai sou tsubuyaitemiseru
もう何も恐くない　そう呟いてみせる
Eventually, everyone ends up alone,
itsuka hito ha hitori ni natte
いつか人は一人になって
And is left with only their memories.
omoide no naka ni ikiteku dake
思い出の中に生きてくだけ
In order to appreciate even sorrow and continue smiling,
kodoku sae aishi waratterareru you ni
孤独さえ愛し笑ってられるように
I'll keep on fighting,
atashi ha tatakaunda
あたしは戦うんだ
I won't show you my tears.
namida nante misenainda
涙なんて見せないんだ
Next Episode Preview
Matsushita Fifth!
So we're locked in...
I look forward to seeing you again.
Trap...
What does this mean?!
We can't divert such a terrifying enemy!
I'll show you one possibility.
Is Kanade all right?
Angel Player...
I'll show it to you physically.
How unwise!
Looks like it's show-time!
Those who cannot keep up will be left behind!
You look busy...
Please be safe, Kanade!